Pierre Mahé

Research Engineer - Machine Learning for Computational Biology 484, allée des Sapins
38250 Lans en Vercors, France

(**)* (+33) 6 82 35 67 89

□ pierre.mahe@biomerieux.com
□ pmahe.github.io/
Married, 3 children.
Born on July 8th, 1979.



Research engineer with a solid expertise in machine learning, I have extensive experience in applying machine learning algorithms to biological data. Over the last decade, I have mainly been involved in clinical microbiology applications, such as identifying bacteria or predicting their antibiotic resistance profiles using various technologies (e.g. mass-spectrometry, imaging and next-generation sequencing). My current interest lies particularly in analyzing genomics data using k-mer based and/or deep-learning approaches.

Education

2003–2006 **Ecole des Mines de Paris (France)**, *Ph.D.*, Machine Learning and Computational Biology.

Graph kernels and kernel methods for chemoinformatics. Supervised by Jean-Philippe Vert, obtained with honors.

2002–2003 Ecole Normale Supérieure de Cachan (France), M.Sc., Machine Learning and Computer Vision. Obtained with honors.

1997–2002 Institut National des Sciences Appliquées (France), French Engineering Degree, Computer Science.

Experience

2016-present Associate Professor (part-time), University Grenoble-Alpes (France)

Teaching statistical machine learning, computational statistics and project management to M.Sc. students.

2008-present Research Engineer, bioMérieux (Grenoble, France)

Providing machine learning expertise to support R&D projects addressing key in vitro diagnostics issues for clinical microbiology, using emerging technologies (e.g. next-generation sequencing, imaging and mass-spectrometry). Mentoring of students and junior employees. Definition, planning and management of R&D projects.

2006–2008 **Post-Doctoral Researcher**, Xerox Research Center Europe (now Naver Labs, Grenoble, France) Statistical learning for machine translation.

Student supervision

2020—present **Teddy Ardouin**, *Ph.D*, Automatic design of PCR primers using deep-generative models. Co-advised with Adeline Leclercq-Samson (University Grenoble-Alpes) and Laurent Drazek (bioMérieux).

- 2021 **Thomas Poulain**, *M.Sc*, Taxonomic classification of microbial sequencing reads by deep-learning.
- 2021 Lina Khodja, M.Sc, Unsupervised representation learning of bacterial genomes.
- 2019 Sylla Camara, M.Sc, Early prediction of antibiotic resistance from time series of microscopy images.
- 2018 Luis Montero, M.Sc, Classification of bacterial 16S genomic sequences by convolutional neural networks.
- 2017 Julia Puig, M.Sc, Semantic segmentation of microscopy images by deep-learning.
- 2017 Antonin Riffard, M.Sc, Targeted resistance genotyping for Mycobacterium tuberculosis.
- 2015 Antoine Bonnefoy, Ph.D (visiting), Sparse multi-task learning for antimicrobial resistance prediction.
- 2011-2014 **Kévin Vervier**, *Ph.D*, Structured machine learning methods for clinical microbiology. Co-advised with Jean-Philippe Vert (Ecole des Mines de Paris, now Google Brain).

Selected publications

2022 Ultra-fast SARS-CoV-2 variant identification from Oxford Nanopore reads using k-mers and local sequencing depth estimation. Meriem El Azami, Magali Jaillard-Dancette, Aurélien Griffon, Maud Tournoud and Pierre Mahé. Submitted to Bioinformatics in March 2022.

- 2020 Interpreting k-mer based signatures for antiobiotic resistance prediction. Magali Jaillard-Dancette, Mattia Palmieri, Alex van Belkum, Pierre Mahé. GigaScience.
- 2019 A large scale evaluation of TBProfiler and Mykrobe for antibiotic resistance prediction in M. tuberculosis. Pierre Mahé, Meriem El Azami, Philippine Barlas, Maud Tournoud. PeerJ.
- 2018 Predicting bacterial resistance phenotypes from whole-genome sequences using k-mers and stability selection. Pierre Mahé, Maud Tournoud. BMC Bioinformatics.
- 2016 Large scale machine learning for metagenomics sequence classification. Kévin Vervier, Pierre Mahé, Maud Tournoud, Jean-Baptiste Veyrieras, Jean-Philippe Vert. Bioinformatics.
- 2016 Joint input/output regularization for structured variable selection in a multi-task framework. Antoine Bonnefoy, Pierre Mahé, Ismael Ouamlil, Jean-Baptiste Veyrieras. Conférence Française d'Apprentissage.
- 2014 Automatic identification of mixed bacterial species fingerprints in a MALDI-TOF mass-spectrum. Pierre Mahé et. al. Bioinformatics.
- 2009 Linguistically enriched word-sequence kernels for discriminative language modeling. Pierre Mahé, Nicola Cancedda. Learning Machine Translation, MIT Press.
- 2009 Graph kernels based on tree-patterns for molecules. Pierre Mahé, Jean-Philippe Vert. Machine Learning
- 2005 Graph kernels for molecular structure-activity relationship analysis with support vector machines. Pierre Mahé, Jean-Philippe Vert. Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling

Full list available at https://scholar.google.fr/citations?user=3yLMPGgAAAAJ

Skills

Data Science: R, python, Unix/bash, C/C++, git, IATEX, keras/tensorflow, scikit-learn.

Machine Learning: broad expertise in supervised and unsupervised learning. Particular interest in deep learning, kernel methods and Lasso penalization for the analysis of structured and high-dimensional data.

Computational Biology: next-generation sequencing, mass spectrometry, image analysis, bioinformatics algorithms, bacterial genomics, clinical microbiology.

Languages: French (native), English (fluent) and Spanish (intermediate).

Personal interests

Rock climbing, hiking, mountain biking.

DIY and renovation work (creation of a 7 person gite - https://www.aufildelans.com/).

Graphical novels.

Struggling to learn the guitar.

References

Available upon request.